The murder happened a little over 21 years ago,
حدثت الجريمة قبل ٢١ عام،
January the 18th, 1991,
١٨ يناير ١٩٩١،
in a small
في
bedroom community
القرية الصغيرة
of Lynwood, California, just a few miles
لينوود في كاليفورنيا، التي تقع
southeast of Los Angeles.
جنوب شرق لوس آنجلوس.
A father came out of his house
خرج الأب من منزله
to tell his teenage son and his five friends
ليخبر ابنه المراهق وأصحابه الخمسة
that it was time for them to stop horsing around
أن يتوقفوا عن اللعب بعنف
on the front lawn and on the sidewalk,
في الساحة الآمامية والشارع،
to get home, finish their schoolwork,
وآن يعودوا لمنازلهم، وينهوا واجبات المدرسة،
and prepare themselves for bed.
ويستعدوا للنوم.
And as the father was administering these instructions,
وبينما كان الأب يلقي تعليماته،
a car drove by, slowly,
مرت سيارة ببطء،
and just after it passed the father and the teenagers,
وبعد ما اجتازتهم،
a hand went out from the front passenger window,
خرجت يد من نافذة مقعد الراكب الأمامي،
and -- "Bam, Bam!" -- killing the father.
"بام بام!" قتلت الأب.
And the car sped off.
وابتعدت السيارة مسرعة.
The police,
الشرطة،
investigating officers, were amazingly efficient.
ضباط التحقيق، كانوا منظمين لدرجة رائعة.
They considered all the usual culprits,
أخذوا جميع المجرمين المعتادين بعين الاعتبار،
and in less than 24 hours, they had selected their suspect:
وفي أقل من ٢٤ ساعة، حددوا المشتبه فيه:
Francisco Carrillo, a 17-year-old kid
فرانسيسكو كاريو، ابن ١٧ عاما
who lived about two or three blocks away
الذي كان يسكن على مقربة
from where the shooting occurred.
من مكان الحادثة.
They found photos of him. They prepared a photo array,
وجدوا صور له، وأعدوا مجموعة من الصور،
and the day after the shooting,
وفي اليوم التالي،
they showed it to one of the teenagers, and he said,
عرضوا الصور على واحد من المراهقين، والذي قال،
"That's the picture.
"هذه هي الصورة.
That's the shooter I saw that killed the father."
هذا هو الشخص الذي قتل الأب."
That was all a preliminary hearing judge had
وكان هذا كافيا لقاضي الجلسة التمهيدية
to listen to, to bind Mr. Carrillo over to stand trial
أن يحيل السيد كاريو إلى محاكمة
for a first-degree murder.
لجريمة قتل من الدرجة الأولى.
In the investigation that followed before the actual trial,
وفي التحقيق الذي جرى قبل المحاكمة الفعلية،
each of the other five teenagers was shown
عرضوا الصور نفسها،
photographs, the same photo array.
على جميع المراهقين الآخرين.
The picture that we best can determine was probably
الصورة التي نستطيع تحديدها، كانت على الغالب
the one that they were shown in the photo array
الصورة التي عرضت عليهم
is in your bottom left hand corner of these mug shots.
كانت هي الصورة التي على الزاوية اليسرى السفلى من هذه المجموعة.
The reason we're not sure absolutely is because
السبب أننا لسنا متأكدين تماما هو
of the nature of evidence preservation
طبيعة حماية الأدلة
in our judicial system,
في نظامنا القضائي،
but that's another whole TEDx talk for later. (Laughter)
ولكن هذا الموضوع يحتاج إلى حديث تيد إكس آخر.(ضحك)
So at the actual trial,
وفي المحاكمة،
all six of the teenagers testified,
شهد جميع المراهقين الستة،
and indicated the identifications they had made
بتحديد الصور نفسها
in the photo array.
في عرض الصور.
He was convicted. He was sentenced to life imprisonment,
تمت إدانة الرجل. حكموا عليه بالسجن مدى الحياة،
and transported to Folsom Prison.
ونقله إلى سجن فولسوم.
So what's wrong?
إذا ما هي المشكلة؟
Straightforward, fair trial, full investigation.
حكم مباشر، محاكمة عادلة، تحقيق كامل.
Oh yes, no gun was ever found.
أوه نعم، لم يجدوا المسدس إطلاقا.
No vehicle was ever identified as being the one
لم يجدوا السيارة
in which the shooter had extended his arm,
التي أخرج منها القاتل ذراعه،
and no person was ever charged with being the driver
ولم يتهموا أي شخص بأن يكون
of the shooter's vehicle.
سائق سيارة القاتل.
And Mr. Carrillo's alibi?
وادعاء السيد كاريو؟
Which of those parents here in the room might not lie
من من الآباء الحاضرين معنا اليوم قد لا يكذب
concerning the whereabouts of your son or daughter
عندما يتعلق الأمر بأين كان إبنه أو إبنته
in an investigation of a killing?
في تحقيق متعلق بجريمة قتل؟
Sent to prison,
أرسل الرجل للسجن
adamantly insisting on his innocence,
وهو مصر تماماً علي أنه برئ
which he has consistently for 21 years.
وإستمر علي هذا الإصرار ل 21 سنة لاحقة
So what's the problem?
حسنا ، مالمشكلة في هذه القصة ؟
The problems, actually, for this kind of case
المشكلة في هذا النوع من القصص
come manyfold from decades of scientific research
تأتي متكررة خلال عقود من البحث العلمي
involving human memory.
متضمنة الذاكرة البشرية
First of all, we have all the statistical analyses
أولاً نحن لدينا كل التحليلات الإحصائية
from the Innocence Project work,
من العمل على مشروع البراءه
where we know that we have, what,
حيث يمكننا ان نعرف ما لدينا، ماذا،
250, 280 documented cases now where people have
٢٥٠،٢٨٠ قضايا موثقه الآن حيث كان الناس
been wrongfully convicted and subsequently exonerated,
أدينوا ظلما وتم تبرئتهم في وقت لاحق،
some from death row, on the basis of later DNA analysis,
بعضهم من عقوبه الاعدام، على أساس تحليل DNA في وقت لاحق،
and you know that over three quarters of all of those cases
وهل تعلم ان اكثر من ثلث ارباع كل قضايا
of exoneration involved only eyewitness identification
التبرئه تضمنت فقط تحديد شهود العيان
testimony during the trial that convicted them.
وشهادتهم خلال المحاكمه التي ادينوا فيها
We know that eyewitness identifications are fallible.
نحن نعلم ان تحديد شهود العيان قابل للخطأ
The other comes from an interesting aspect
الآخر يأتي من جانب مثير للاهتمام
of human memory that's related to various brain functions
من الذاكرة البشرية التي تتعلق بوظائف المخ المختلفة
but I can sum up for the sake of brevity here
لكن يمكنني أن ألخص من أجل الإيجاز
in a simple line:
في سطر بسيط
The brain abhors a vacuum.
الدماغ يمقت فكرة الفراغ
Under the best of observation conditions,
حتي في أفضل ظروف المراقبة
the absolute best,
الأفضل بدون أي شك
we only detect, encode and store in our brains
نحن فقط نلقط ونحلل ونسجل في عقولنا
bits and pieces of the entire experience in front of us,
أجزاء صغيرة من مجمل مايحدث أمامنا
and they're stored in different parts of the brain.
وهذه الاجزاء تسجل في أجزاء مختلفة من الدماغ
So now, when it's important for us to be able to recall
والآن عندما يكون من الضروري لنا أن نستحضر منها
what it was that we experienced,
ماذا حدث وإختبرناه بأعيننا
we have an incomplete, we have a partial store,
سيكون لدينا في مخزون ناقص وجزئي
and what happens?
ثم ماذا سيحصل؟
Below awareness, with no requirement for any kind of
في اللاوعي ، ومع عدم وجود أي نوع من
motivated processing, the brain fills in information
الدوافع ، سيقوم العقل بملء الفراغات في القصة
that was not there,
من معلومات ليست موجودة
not originally stored,
لم تخزن في لحظة الحدث
from inference, from speculation,
بل جاءت من الإستنتاج والتخمين
from sources of information that came to you,
ومن المعلومات التي تكون وصلت إليه من مصادر متعددة
as the observer, after the observation.
تماما كما المراقب بعد المراقبة
But it happens without awareness such that
لكن ذلك يحدث من دون وعي
you don't, aren't even cognizant of it occurring.
انت لا تدرك حدوثها.
It's called reconstructed memories.
انه يدعى ترميم الذاكره
It happens to us in all the aspects of our life, all the time.
ان يحدث لنا في كل جوانب حياتنا، كل الوقت.
It was those two considerations, among others --
كان هنالك إعتبارين من بين الإعتبارات -
reconstructed memory, the fact about the eyewitness fallibility --
ترميم الذاكره، حقيقه قابليه الخطأ لشهود العيان
that was part of the instigation
التي كانت جزء من التحميس
for a group of appeal attorneys
لمجموعه من محامي الطعن
led by an amazing lawyer named Ellen Eggers
بقياده المحامي الرائع الين ايقيرس
to pool their experience and their talents together
لتجميع خبراتهم ومواهبهم معا
and petition a superior court
ويقدموا التماسا إلى المحكمة العليا
for a retrial for Francisco Carrillo.
لإعادة محاكمته لفرانسيسكو كاريو.
They retained me, as a forensic neurophysiologist,
وكلوني، بصفتي طبيب شرعي لعلم وظائف الاعصاب
because I had expertise
لأن لدي خبره
in eyewitness memory identification,
في ذاكرة شاهد عيان،
which obviously makes sense for this case, right?
الذي من الواضح انه منطقي لهذه الحالة، أليس كذلك؟
But also because I have expertise and testify about
لكن ايضا لأن لدي الخبره وشهدت حول
the nature of human night vision.
طبيعه الرؤيه الليليه للانسان.
Well, what's that got to do with this?
حسنا، ما علاقته بالقضيه؟
Well, when you read through the case materials
حسنا، عندما تقرآ في ملابسات القضيه
in this Carrillo case,
في قضيه كاريو،
one of the things that suddenly strikes you is that
واحدة من الأشياء التي تباغتك فجأة هو أن
the investigating officers said the lighting was good
هو ان ضباط التحقيق يفيدون الأضاءه كانت جيده
at the crime scene, at the shooting.
في ساحه الجريمه، عند اطلاق النار
All the teenagers testified during the trial
كل المراهقين الذين شهدوا خلال المحاكمه
that they could see very well.
كانوا يمكنهم الرؤيه بشكل جيد
But this occurred in mid-January,
ولكن حدث هذا في منتصف شهر يناير،
in the Northern Hemisphere, at 7 p.m. at night.
في نصف الكرة الشمالي، عند الساعة 7 مساء في الليل.
So when I did the calculations
اذا عندما قمت بالحسابات
for the lunar data and the solar data
للبيانات القمريه والبيانات الشمسيه
at that location on Earth at the time of the incident
لذلك الموقع من الكره الارضيه في ذلك الوقت لجريمه
of the shooting, all right,
اطلاق النار، حسنا،
it was well past the end of civil twilight
لقد كان بعد انتهاء الشفق المدني بوقت جيد
and there was no moon up that night.
وكان لايوجد قمر في تلك الليله
So all the light in this area from the sun and the moon
اذا كل الاضاءه في تلك المنطقه من الشمس والقمر
is what you see on the screen right here.
هو ماتراه في الشاشه الان.
The only lighting in that area had to come
الضوء الوحيد في تلك المنطقه عليه ان يأتي
from artificial sources,
من مصدر صناعي
and that's where I go out and I do the actual reconstruction
وهنا حيث اخرج انا واعيد فعليا بناء
of the scene with photometers, with various measures
المشهد مع اضواء، بمختلف المقادير
of illumination and various other measures of
من الإضاءة وغيرها من التدابير المختلفة
color perception, along with special cameras
لإدراك اللون، مع كاميرات خاصه
and high-speed film, right?
وعالية السرعة، حسنا؟
Take all the measurements and record them, right?
اخذ جميع القياسات وتسجيلها، حسنا؟
And then take photographs, and this is what the scene
ثم أخذ الصور، وهذا ما المشهد
looked like at the time of the shooting
بدى عليه في ذلك الوقت عند اطلاق النار
from the position of the teenagers
من موضع المراهقين
looking at the car going by and shooting.
وهم يرون السياره تمر ويحدث اطلاق النار
This is looking directly across the street
هنا الرؤيه مباشره عبر الشارع
from where they were standing.
من حيث كانوا يقفون.
Remember, the investigating officers' report said
تذكر، تقرير ضباط التحقيق ذكر
the lighting was good.
الاضاءه كانت جيده.
The teenagers said they could see very well.
المراهقين قالوا ان كان بإمكانهم الرؤيه بشكل جيد.
This is looking down to the east,
هنا الرؤيه تطل على الشرق
where the shooting vehicle sped off,
حيث المركبه التي اطلقت النار ابطئت حركتها
and this is the lighting directly behind the father
وهنا الاضاءه مباشره من وراء الاب
and the teenagers.
والمراهقين.
As you can see, it is at best poor.
كما ترون، انها الافقر في احسن الاحوال
No one's going to call this well-lit, good lighting,
لا احد يمكنه القول انها اضيئت جيداً، اضاءه جيده
and in fact, as nice as these pictures are,
في واقع الأمر، لطيفا كما هي هذه الصور،
and the reason we take them is I knew I was going to have to testify in court,
والسبب في اخذنا لهذه الصور هو انني علمت ان علي ان أشهد في المحكمه،
and a picture is worth more than a thousand words
والصوره تساوي اكثر من الف كلمه
when you're trying to communicate numbers,
عندما تحاول التواصل بالارقام
abstract concepts like lux, the international measurement
مفاهيم مجرده مثل لوكس، مقاييس عالميه
of illumination, the Ishihara color perception test values.
للإضاءة، واختبار قيم تصور ايشيهارا للون.
When you present those to people who are not well-versed
عندما تقدم هذه المعلومات للناس غير المتمكنين جيدا
in those aspects of science and that, they become
في هذه الجوانب العلميه، في هذه الحاله تصبح مثل
salamanders in the noonday sun. It's like
السلمندر في يوم مشمس الظهر. انها مثل
talking about the tangent of the visual angle, all right?
الحديث عن مماس الزاوية البصرية، حسنا؟
Their eyes just glaze over, all right?
عيونهم تحدق بعيداً، حسنا؟
A good forensic expert also has to be a good educator,
خبرتي كطبيب شرعي هي ايضا ان تكون معلم جيدا،
a good communicator, and that's part of the reason
محاورا جيدا، وهذا جزءا من السبب
why we take the pictures, to show not only
لاخذنا لهذه الصور، لنريهم ليس فقط
where the light sources are, and what we call the spill,
اين مصدر الضوء، وما نسميه تسرب،
the distribution, but also so that it's easier
التوزيع ، لكن ايضا ليكون من الاسهل
for the trier of fact to understand the circumstances.
لتبت في الوقائع بعد فهم الملابسات
So these are some of the pictures that, in fact,
لذلك فان هذه هي بعض من الصور التي، في الواقع،
I used when I testified,
استعملتها عندما شهدت
but more importantly were, to me as a scientist,
ولكن الأهم كان بالنسبة لي كعالم،
are those readings, the photometer readings,
هي تلك القراءت، قراءات المضواء،
which I can then convert into actual predictions
التي يمكنني تحويلها بعد ذلك لتوقعات فعليه
of the visual capability of the human eye
للقدره البصريه للعين البشريه
under those circumstances,
تحت تلك الظروف
and from my readings that I recorded at the scene
ومن خلال قراءاتي المسجله في المشهد
under the same solar and lunar conditions
تحت نفس الظروف الشمسيه والقمريه
at the same time, so on and so forth, right,
في نفس ذلك الوقت، هكذا وهكذا دواليك، حسنا
I could predict
يمكنني التنبؤ
that there would be no reliable color perception,
انه لن يكون من الممكن وجود إدراك لون موثوق به،
which is crucial for face recognition,
وهو أمر حاسم بالنسبة التعرف على الوجه،
and that there would be only scotopic vision,
وبذلك لن يكون هناك الا رؤيه ظلاميه
which means there would be very little resolution,
وذلك يعني ان هناك القليل جدا من دقة الرؤية
what we call boundary or edge detection,
التي نسميها الحدود أو الكشف عن الحافة،
and that furthermore, because the eyes would have been
وعلاوة على ذلك أن، لأن العيون كانت
totally dilated under this light, the depth of field,
متوسعة تماما تحت ذلك ضوء، فإن عمق الميدان،
the distance at which you can focus and see details,
المسافه التي تمكننا من ان نركز ونرى التفاصيل
would have been less than 18 inches away.
ستكون اقل من ١٨ بوصة بعيدا
I testified to that to the court,
شهدت انا بذلك في المحكمه،
and while the judge was very attentive,
وبينما كان القاضي يقظاً جدا،
it had been a very, very long hearing
لقد كانت جلسه سماع طويله جدا
for this petition for a retrial, and as a result,
لهذا الالتماس لإعادة محاكمته، ونتيجة لذلك،
I noticed out of the corner of my eye
لقد لاحظت من زاوية عيني
that I thought that maybe the judge was going to need
ذلك انني اعتقد انه من الممكن ان القاضي يحتاج
a little more of a nudge
قليلا من الدفعه
than just more numbers.
من مجرد ارقام
And here I became a bit audacious,
وهنا اصبحت جريئا قليلا،
and I turned
والتفت
and I asked the judge,
وسألت القاضي
I said, "Your Honor, I think you should go out
قلت "معاليك، اعتقد انه يجب عليك الخروج
and look at the scene yourself."
ومشاهده مسرح الجريمه بنفسك"
Now I may have used a tone which was more like a dare
ربما كنت استعملت نبره صوت متحديه اكثر
than a request — (Laughter) —
من كونها طلبا ----(ضحك)---
but nonetheless, it's to this man's credit and his courage
ولكن على الرغم من ذلك، انها شرف لهذا الرجل وشجاعته
that he said, "Yes, I will."
أن قال: "نعم، سأفعل."
A shocker in American jurisprudence.
ومفاجأه في الفقه القانوني الامريكي
So in fact, we found the same identical conditions,
هذا وفي الواقع، وجدنا نفس الشروط متطابقة،
we reconstructed the entire thing again,
قمنا بإعاده بناء مسرح الجريمه من جديد
he came out with an entire brigade of sheriff's officers
اتى القاضي مع كامل لواء ضباط الشريف
to protect him in this community, all right? (Laughter)
لحمايته في هذا المجتمع، حسنا؟ (ضحك)
We had him stand actually slightly in the street,
جعلناه يقف قليلا علي الشارع
so closer to the suspect vehicle, the shooter vehicle,
قريبا للمركبه المشتبه عليه، مركبه مطلق النار،
than the actual teenagers were,
مما كان عليه المراهقون
so he stood a few feet from the curb
فوقف على بعد بضعة أقدام من حافة الرصيف
toward the middle of the street.
نحو منتصف الشارع
We had a car that came by,
جلعنا سياره تمر من جانبنا
same identical car as described by the teenagers, right?
سيارة مطابقة لتلك التي وصفها المراهقين، حسنا؟
It had a driver and a passenger,
كان لها سائق وراكب اخر بجانبه،
and after the car had passed the judge by,
وبعد ان مرت السياره بجانب القاضي
the passenger extended his hand,
الراكب مد يده
pointed it back to the judge as the car continued on,
مشيرا بها للقاضي بينما السياره تستمر بالسير،
just as the teenagers had described it, right?
كما قد وصفها المراهقين، حسنا؟
Now, he didn't use a real gun in his hand,
الآن، نحن لم نستخدم مسدس حقيقي في يده
so he had a black object in his hand that was similar
لذلك كان معه شيء اسود في يديه كان مشابه
to the gun that was described.
للمسدس الذي تم وصفه
He pointed by, and this is what the judge saw.
اشار به، وهذا هو ما رأه القاضي
This is the car 30 feet away from the judge.
هذه السياره تبعد ٣٠ قدما عن القاضي
There's an arm sticking out of the passenger side
هناك يد تخرج من جانب الراكب
and pointed back at you.
ومشيره اليك.
That's 30 feet away.
هذه ٣٠ قدم بعيدا
Some of the teenagers said that in fact the car
بعض المراهقين قالوا بأن السياره في الواقع
was 15 feet away when it shot.
كانت ١٥ قدم بعيدا عندما اطلقت النار
Okay. There's 15 feet.
حسنا، هذه ١٥ قدم
At this point, I became a little concerned.
في هذه النقطه، اصبحت قلق قليلا
This judge is someone you'd never want to play poker with.
هذا القاضي هو شخص لا تريد أن تلعب معه لعبة البوكر.
He was totally stoic. I couldn't see a twitch of his eyebrow.
كان جامدا تماما. لم أتمكن من رؤية يحرك من حاجبه.
I couldn't see the slightest bend of his head.
لم اتمكن من رؤيه اقل حركه لرأسه
I had no sense of how he was reacting to this,
لم يكن لدي أي فكرة عن رد فعله لهذا،
and after he looked at this reenactment,
وبعد ان نظر لهذا التجديد
he turned to me and he says,
التفت الي وقال،
"Is there anything else you want me to look at?"
"هل يوجد شيء اخر تريدني ان اطلع عليه؟"
I said, "Your honor," and I don't know whether I was
قلت"معاليك"وأنا لا أعرف ما إذا كنت
emboldened by the scientific measurements that I had
جريئا بسب القياسات العلميه التي احملها
in my pocket and my knowledge that they are accurate,
في جيبي و معرفتي انها دقيقه
or whether it was just sheer stupidity,
او انها كانت ضرب من الغباء
which is what the defense lawyers thought — (Laughter) —
والتي هي بالتحديد ما اعتقده المحاميين (ضحك)
when they heard me say,
عندما سمعوني اقول
"Yes, Your Honor, I want you stand right there
"نعم، معاليك اريدك ان تقف هناك بالتحديد"
and I want the car to go around the block again
واريد ان تلف السياره الحي من جديد
and I want it to come and I want it to stop
واريدها ان تأتي وتقف
right in front of you, three to four feet away,
امامك مباشره ٣ الى ٤ اقدام بعيدا
and I want the passenger to extend his hand
واريد الراكب ان يمد يده
with a black object and point it right at you,
مع الشيء الاسود ويصوبه نحوك تماما
and you can look at it as long as you want."
ويمكنك ان تنظر اليه طالما تريد
And that's what he saw. (Laughter)
وهذا ما راءه (ضحك)
You'll notice, which was also in my test report,
ستلاحظ، الذي كان أيضا في تقرير اختباري،
all the dominant lighting is coming from the north side,
جميع الإضاءة السائدة تأتي من الجانب الشمالي،
which means that the shooter's face would
هذا يعني ان وجه مطلق النار سيكون
have been photo-occluded. It would have been backlit.
صورته متغطيه، كان من الخلفية.
Furthermore, the roof of the car
علاوة على ذلك، فإن سقف السيارة
is causing what we call a shadow cloud inside the car
يسبب ما يدعى سحابه ظل بداخل السياره
which is making it darker.
وذلك يجعله اشد قتامه.
And this is three to four feet away.
وهذا على بعد ٣ الى ٤ اقدام
Why did I take the risk?
لماذا اخذت المجازفه
I knew that the depth of field was 18 inches or less.
علمت ان عمق الميدان كان ١٨ بوصة او اقل
Three to four feet, it might as well have been
٣ الى ٤ اقدام ، كان من الممكن ان يكون
a football field away.
ببعد ملعب لكرة القدم.
This is what he saw.
هذا هو ما رأه
He went back, there was a few more days of evidence
عاد مجددا، كان هناك بضعة أيام أخرى من الأدلة
that was heard. At the end of it,
التي استُمع لها. في النهايه
he made the judgment that he was going to grant
قدم الحكم أنه سيقوم بمنح
the petition for a retrial.
التماس لإعادة المحاكمه.
And furthermore, he released Mr. Carrillo
علاوه على ذلك،أفرج عن السيد كاريو
so that he could aid in the preparation of his own defense
بحيث يتمكن من المساعدة في إعداد الدفاع عن نفسه
if the prosecution decided to retry him.
إذا قررت النيابة إعادة محاكمته.
Which they decided not to.
والذي قرروا هم عدم فعل ذلك
He is now a freed man. (Applause)
وهو الان رجلاً حرا (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is him embracing his grandmother-in-law.
هذا هو يحتضن جدة زوجته.
He -- His girlfriend was pregnant when he went to trial,
هو -- كان لديه رفيقه حامل عندما ذهب للمحكمه
right? And she had a little baby boy.
حسنا؟ انجبت هي ولدا صغير
He and his son are both attending Cal State, Long Beach
هو وابنه على حد سواء يعيشون في ولايه كاليفورنيا، لونغ بيتش
right now taking classes. (Applause)
هو الان يأخذون دورسا. (تصفيق)
And what does this example --
وما يعنيه هذا المثال--
what's important to keep in mind for ourselves?
ما هو مهم أن نأخذه في الاعتبار لأنفسنا؟
First of all, there's a long history of antipathy
بادئ ذي بدء، هناك تاريخ طويل من الكراهية
between science and the law
بين القانون والعلم
in American jurisprudence.
في الفقه الامريكي
I could regale you with horror stories of ignorance
ويمكنني أن امتعكم بقصص رعب من الجهل
over decades of experience as a forensic expert
على مدى عقود من الخبره كطبيب شرعي
of just trying to get science into the courtroom.
من مجرد محاولة لإدخال العلم في قاعة المحكمة
The opposing council always fight it and oppose it.
مجلس المعارضة يحاربها دائما ويعارضها.
One suggestion is that all of us become much more
اقتراح واحد هو أن كل واحد منا يصبح أكثر
attuned to the necessity, through policy,
تفهما للضرورة، من خلال السياسة،
through procedures,
من خلال إجراءات،
to get more science in the courtroom,
لإدخال العلم لقاعه المحكمه
and I think one large step toward that
واعتقد ان خطوه كبيره نحو ذلك ستكون
is more requirements,
متطلبات اكثر
with all due respect to the law schools,
مع كل الاحترام لمدارس القانون
of science, technology, engineering, mathematics
العلوم، التكنولوجيا، الهندسه، الرياضيات
for anyone going into the law,
لاي شخص سيدرس القانون
because they become the judges.
لانهم سيصبحون القضاه
Think about how we select our judges in this country.
فكر في كيفيه اختيارنا للقضاه في بلدنا
It's very different than most other cultures. All right?
مختلف تماما عن اغلب الثقافات الاخرى. حسنا؟
The other one that I want to suggest,
الامر الاخر هو انني اود ان اقترح
the caution that all of us have to have,
الحذر الذي يجب علينا جميعنا ان نتخذه
I constantly have to remind myself,
علي دائما ان اذكر نفسي
about just how accurate are the memories
فقط حول مدى دقة الذكريات
that we know are true, that we believe in?
التي نعلم انها حقيقه، التي نؤمن بها؟
There is decades of research,
هناك عقود من الابحاث
examples and examples of cases like this,
نماذج ونماذج من قضايا مثل هذه،
where individuals
حيث يؤمن افراد
really, really believe. None of those teenagers
حقا، حقا يؤمنون . اي من هؤلاء المراهقين
who identified him
الذين عرفوا المجرم
thought that they were picking the wrong person.
فكروا انهم اختاروا الشخص الخطأ
None of them thought they couldn't see the person's face.
لم يعتقد احدهم منهم انه لم يتمكن من رؤيه وجه المجرم.
We all have to be very careful.
علينا جميعا ان نكون حذرين.
All our memories are reconstructed memories.
كل ذكرياتنا هي ذكريا مرممه.
They are the product of what we originally experienced
هم نتاج ما شهدناه في الأصل
and everything that's happened afterwards.
وكل ما حدث بعد ذلك.
They're dynamic.
انها ديناميكيه
They're malleable. They're volatile,
انها لينه، انها متقلبه
and as a result, we all need to remember to be cautious,
لذلك علينا ان نتذكر ان نكون حذرين
that the accuracy of our memories
ان دقة ذاكرتنا
is not measured in how vivid they are
لا تقاس بمدى قوتها
nor how certain you are that they're correct.
او مدى ثقتك بصحتها
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم (تصفيق)